Hey, welcome back to the centerfuge
where we go through the claims made on
health podcasts and back it up or strike
it down with a series of studies. In
this episode, continuing the J Shetty
podcast series, we'll be getting into
the claims made by Alyssa Goodman, a gut
cleanse expert according to J. Shedy, as
well as a certified holistic
nutritionist according to Miss Goodman's
website. We'll be covering three main
topics. One, a cleanse containing many
ingredients including kefir, lemon,
ginger, and more, and how these
ingredients improve our health. Two,
activated charcoal for a gut cleanse,
including a few additional ingredients.
And three, pooping three times a day is
optimal. Anything under that is
suboptimal. We'll see if that's true.
So, without further ado, let's get into
it. And oh, and all the studies are
linked for you in the description.
>> Walk us through. So, walk us through the
core needs that people come to you with.
So, you said they do a there's a gut
cleanse. Walk us through the different
cleanses that people need in their life.
>> Um, so the regular cleanse is really
I'll tell you a little bit about what's
on it. Um, there's a detox tonic on it
with coconut kafir, which is a probiotic
drink.
>> I love coconut kafir. I am a big fan of
probiotics and I love coconut kafir,
cocoa yo, and there's a lot of great
products out there on the market. Then
it has chlorophyll, apple cider vinegar,
lemon, ginger in there. And then there's
my homemade super seed bar. Um, then you
basically get a bone broth or vegan
broth. Um, our bone broth is really
gelatinous and so there's a lot of
collagen which I love. And then we get
you get different salads for the week,
different salad dressings, fermented
vegetables, you get different soups for
the for the night time, and then you get
lattes for the evening. Then you also
get digestive enzymes and you get
magnesium. So to make sure that
everything's working properly because
people going from an animal protein diet
into a plant-based legumes and beans can
disrupt their stomach. It also a lot of
vegetables can as well. So there's that
one. There's a three-day.
>> So with that one, how walk us through.
So are you encouraging people to not
have dinners in that? Is that like soup
is dinner? Yes.
>> Or they could have soup for lunch and do
the salad for dinner. So, it's not super
strict. Um, a lot of people who exercise
a ton will add a little bit of animal
protein, you know, to the meal
potentially, and it doesn't take you
away from the cleanse. So, again, you're
just getting tons of vegetables, you're
getting anti-inflammatory,
you know, nourishing, nurturing foods.
So, um, that, you know, that one is like
my regular one that has been going on
for 9 years. Sometimes it blows my mind
because the tonic's been on there for 9
years. The bar has been on there. Like
it's crazy that things are still
popular. Um people buy the tonics and
the bars separately. And then the gut
cleanse has um activated charcoal on
there. So,
>> okay, there's a lot here. So, Miss
Goodman went over a bunch of ingredients
and usually we'd want to have some form
of outcome like heart disease or
dementia or something that we can
attribute those ingredients to, but
nothing was mentioned. So, I'm kind of
flying by the seat of my pants here.
That's actually an expression I don't
fully understand, but we'll put that
aside. We can just look at the general
health. So, essentially use a wide net
to understand if these ingredients are
helpful in any capacity. And then I'm
going to focus in on gut health since
that's what we're talking about with
cleanses. So, the first was coconut
kafir kefir kafir kaf. Let me know kafir
being a fermented milk. There are no
studies on coconut kafir. I may actually
change my pronunciation throughout
because it's a very uncomfortable word
for whatever reason. Anyway, on coconut
kafir other than studies looking at its
formulation and ingredients, but that
doesn't tell us if it actually helps us
with anything. So, if we broaden the
scope to kafir as a whole, we get a
bunch more results like positive effects
in people with type two diabetes or
people with fatty liver disease and
more. To be completely honest, these
studies aren't all that impressive
showing mild effects or suffering from
poor methodology.
Still, that doesn't mean that kefir or
kafir isn't effective. And there are
studies showing changes in gut
microbiome from consuming kafir. Now, I
think I'd put it this way. There's no
good evidence for coconut specific
kafir, but there is some evidence across
multiple randomized control trials that
kafir kefir can be a benefit. However,
the health effects up to now are very
mild like improvements in insulin and
insulin resistance. The next ingredient
mentioned was chlorophyll. And frankly,
again, like the coconut kafir, there's
very little evidence using chlorophyll
alone, except for one very specific use,
which I was pleasantly surprised by,
microtoxins and liver cancer.
Essentially, there are several small
studies that tested the consumption of
chlorophyll or chlorophyllin, a more
stable version of chlorophyll on the
ability to prevent a micotoxin called
aphletoxin, which honestly sounds like a
bad AFLAC commercial from entering our
bloodstream. Ultimately, this matters
because there's been links to this
micotoxin being linked to liver cancer
in China. And since the toxin is found
from molds found in many foods, the
researchers wanted to know if they could
prevent its uptake. The answer was yes.
Chlorophyll binds this micotoxin and
stops it from being absorbed. So,
surprisingly, at least to me, there's a
little bit of evidence in favor of using
chlorophyll, especially as a protective
agent against molds. However, I need to
stress that this comes from only two
small studies and there would need to be
much more research before we could
definitively say that it protects
against liver cancer directly. Next was
apple cider vinegar and I've actually
done some analyses on this before which
ultimately concluded in some mild
effects lowering blood fats in insulin
resistant individuals as one that I can
remember. But when we look at gut
specific effects, there's also some
small studies indicating ACV, that's
what the cool call kids abbreviate apple
cider vinegar, by the way, [laughter]
slows gastric emptying, meaning that the
stomach has a sphincter at the bottom
that controls when the food passes from
the stomach to the intestine. ACV slows
it down, meaning that the sphincter
remains closed for longer, keeping food
in the stomach. Now the GER there is a
gastric emptying rate and if the boxes
are lower that means reduced speed. So
the ACV condition shows reduced speed.
Granted the effect is pretty small. Plus
this study was tiny and it was in type 1
diabetics. So is is this necessarily
applicable to most others? Probably not
something to really worry over.
Alternatively, might I interest you in
some studies on mice? No. Then possibly
amput cuisine by looking at the impact
that ACV has in shrimp.
Yes, you heard that correctly. Shrimp,
the water roaches of the world. The
point here being there's definitely
studies on apple cider vinegar and it
probably has some mild health benefits,
but there's very weak evidence at this
point in relation to gut health. Another
mentioned ingredient is lemon. Good old
lemon. Now, I know this is a popular one
among health influencers. They love that
stuff. I like lemon juice and I add it
to my water on a regular basis. But does
that mean that it's actually effective?
Possibly. In fact, there's studies
looking at kidney stones. And in fact,
there are bigger studies unlike the
little middly pitily ones that we've
been discussing up to now. And in this
study, they discovered that lemon juice
actually helped reduce the recurrence of
kidney stones. Now, there's plenty of
nuance that uh were kind of blowing
past, like the fact that these people
already had issues with kidney stones,
so we don't know if this would
necessarily apply to the general
population. However, a bigger study in a
prestigious journal, The Lancet,
indicates that lemon juice may be a go
on that front, too. One issue brought up
is that a lot of people dropped out
because of gastrointestinal discomfort.
So, there's definitely pros and cons and
probably only useful for people with
kidney stone issues. Finally, if you're
a person who is trying to keep their
blood sugar spikes down, there's one
study that looked at the effect of lemon
juice on the outcome and showed a pretty
substantial reduction in blood glucose
spikes. But if you've seen the last
episode of the centerfuge, then you know
what I think about these glucose spikes.
They're a lot less straightforward than
glucose go up, glucose bad. I'd
encourage you to check out that episode.
I'll link it for you. And as for lemon
juice, on the gut health aspect, there's
no evidence. Yes, there are a few
studies on extracts, but uh there are
none on the actual lemon juice itself.
So, the lemon juice angle is a bit of a
dud. It may uh have some benefits, but
they're incredibly niche and there's a
lot more nothingness than there is of
hard evidence. In a similar vein, ginger
was another mentioned. Surprisingly,
there are multiple studies for ginger
and gut health. Instead of listing them
all off, I'll just reference this one
systematic review because it combines
the studies and ultimately came to the
same conclusion as I did. Not much
there. [laughter]
Ginger has been used against irritable
bowel syndrome to assess changes in
gastric emptying, the same thing that we
discussed earlier, and changes in the
microbiome. Across all of these, there's
either mild or no effect. The most
consistent finding was against nausea
and vomiting. There is a signal on that
front. But again, if we broaden that to
overall health, there may be a bit more
like mild effects on blood cholesterol,
glu glucose levels, uh possibly on blood
pressure. So again, some evidence though
not blinding and mostly away from the
gut health aspect. The second and last I
will cover is bone broth. I know this is
one of a favorites for health
influencers, too. I have a bad news,
though. There is a review that makes the
argument for bone broth being helpful in
gut health, which might mean that
there's evidence, but it's a narrative
review where the researchers make the
argument, but not necessarily based on
strong human evidence. In fact, they
basically make the argument based on
other research on specific sections of
the bone broth, like the amino acids or
the minerals. These aren't bad
arguments, per se, but they can't point
to human evidence because there isn't
any solid evidence for gut health. This
is one of those situations where someone
might uh link a review and claim that
the review is evidence for something.
But when you look at the evidence
presented within that review, you
realize that it's a lot of wishful
thinking, a lot of hypothesizing and
speculation. It has value, but it isn't
real strong evidence. That said, beyond
bone broth, looking at collagen, which
is a big component, I've covered those
topics several times before, and I'm a
fan of collagen regardless of the
source. I'll uh link my deep dives for
you instead of repeating it all here. In
this context, bone broth has almost no
scientific evidence other than the
mechanisms and a little bit of animal
research. No substantiative human
research, however. Finally, let's
discuss magnesium. This one has
significantly more evidence in its favor
like long-term studies indicating
benefit against type two diabetes,
inverse relationships with death as a
whole, and more coming from randomized
control trials as well. But when it
comes to gut health, the most common and
well-known role of magnesium is to, how
do I say this delicately?
Blow it out your backside. Magnesium
oxide is particularly good and has been
shown to act similarly to a laxative. If
that's to be interpreted as a cleanse is
a different story. It may feel that way,
but as far as I'm aware, your body
doesn't need to have you help it clear
your colon for it to experience
improvements in health. Still, I suppose
some people feel that it helps and it
definitely has an abrupt effect to put
it mildly. Overall, magnesium may be one
of the more sciencebacked minerals or
compounds brought up. One last thing
that I'll say before uh we move on.
Notice how spotty the research is for
most of this stuff. Now, I would think
of all this in two actionable ways. One,
you are a strict science person like me.
And in that case, most of these
ingredients leave mass amounts to be
desired when it comes to gut health and
even general health as a whole. Not much
of this is strongly backed by science,
and you may want to avoid this cleanse
on that basis alone. Or two, if you're
mildly interested in the science, but
you'd be willing to experiment on
yourself, this lack of strong scientific
evidence doesn't bother you as much and
self-experimentation is more worthwhile.
They're both correct choices so long as
you're educated on the evidence
surrounding those ingredients. Now,
let's move on to claim number two.
>> Walk us through that.
>> What activated charcoal? So, I love
activated charcoal because it lowers
bacterial loads in your gut. Wait, how
do you eat activated charcoal?
>> You take a pill,
>> right? Okay.
>> You can you can put it in a drink and
you know, you could put it in the detox
tonic um or in water or whatever, but
you take it's a pill. It's a very strong
pill. Um and I have found when I had
insulin resistant clients who couldn't
lose weight, you know, weight resistant
clients, their insulin was high, their
gut bacteria was too high. So, I would
put them on five days of activated
charcoal and lower their insulin levels,
which was like fantastic. So, that's how
the gut cleanse came about. So, they get
activated charcoal, they still get the
enzymes, they get the magnesium. Um, but
they get chia pudding, they get
sauerkraut, they still get the um detox
tonic, they don't get the bar cuz a
little too much sugar. Um, I don't want
sugar for them because of the bacteria.
And then they get everything else that's
pretty similar. And the nighttime is a
Tulsi tea. Um, you know that holy basil
is one of my favorites. It's
anti-inflammatory and great for the gut,
great for sleep. Um, so that's my that's
the other cleanse that I love. And so
what I'm trying to do for people is
really clean them out. Um, my those
clients are the ones that have a little
bit of constipation issues, like aren't
going to the bathroom regularly. Um, and
they're by the end of the week, they're
going two and three times a day.
>> Wow.
>> Like it that's another crazy thing.
>> Okay, this is a specific gut cleanse.
Unlike the last one where I had to
decide to look at overall health and
gut, in this case we can just focus on
the gut. The main ingredient is
activated charcoal. So the question is,
is there any scientific evidence for
activated charcoal on the gut? This is
going to be fun. I say that because we
have studies on gas production as in are
you gassy after a meal if you consume
activated charcoal? In this study,
researchers fed people a non-groucing
meal or a gas producing meal which
involved beans. Good old beans. However,
they also fed them activated charcoal or
placebo for the gas producing meal. And
here were the results. Now, by results,
I mean they measured the number of times
that people farted indicated by flattus
events on the vertical axis. Notice how
one line goes up. That's the bean meal
without the activated charcoal. However,
the white box line is the same meal with
activated charcoal. So, clearly
activated charcoal worked in reducing
gaseousness of the intestines. I never
thought this would be a major discussion
topic on physionic, but it is part of
the body. So, here we are. Now, I'd be
remiss not to mention that not all
studies agree. Some studies find no
effect. So, I'd put this in the same
category of there isn't strong or clear
evidence in favor of activated charcoal
on gassing up those sitting next to you
as you blame the dog. Still, gassiness
isn't all-encompassing for gut health,
and Miss Goodman discusses the
microbiome. She specifically says it
lowers bacterial load, and there's zero
scientific evidence of that. I couldn't
find any studies indicating that to be
true. Though there are some studies that
look at activated charcoal and gut
microbiome and they show no effect over
several days of consumption across
multiple measures. This of course still
doesn't mean that it doesn't work in
other ways. For example, there's a study
on its interaction with antibiotics
which is actually pretty interesting.
And again, nothing shows lowering
bacterial load or even changing the
microbiome meaningfully. In the end,
that's about it. That's what we have.
Some FART research, no signs of changes
to the microbiome on its own, and little
else up to now. So, the claims are
scientifically at least unsubstantiated.
But there's one more thing that
activated charcoal apparently does. It
lowers insulin resistance. According to
Miss Goodman, that one is a big old
goose egg and not a golden one. There
are no studies backing that claim. So, I
realize the second crowd from earlier
might chime in here at some point with,
"Well, I tried it and my blood sugar
dropped 20 points." And that's all well
and good, but the advantage of studies
is that we can isolate things through
single interventions. In this case,
activated charcoal. So if we take Miss
Goodman's protocol, unless the only
thing that they changed was the
activated charcoal, which we know isn't
the case, then we can't say with any
confidence that the activated charcoal
is a reason for these effects. The
disadvantage of studies is that they
require a lot of time, money, and
effort. So it's slowgoing even with
literally thousands of scientists
working on this stuff every day. In
short, from a scientific perspective,
there's no evidence currently that
indicates activated charcoal reduces
insulin resistance. And if we get into
the three other ingredients mentioned
really quickly, the chia pudding, which
I assume is made of chia seeds, the
sauerkraut, and the holy basil, which is
basil blessed by God on the
manufacturing floor. There isn't a ton
on chia seeds in the microbiome, but
there is evidence it improves bowel
movement, so that's looking good. The
sauerkraut angle is even more convincing
with several studies that indicate that
sauerkraut has positive effects on gut
health, including the microbiome. For
example, this study, the participants
consumed two versions of sauerkraut and
their IBS symptoms, irritable bowel
syndrome or irritable bowel disease,
excuse me, symptoms were marketkedly
improved, as seen here. It's a little
off-putting at first, but the higher the
lines go, the worse the IBS symptoms
based on the 500point scale. Both lines,
blue and green, are sauerkraut
conditions, but they both show
improvements over 8 weeks. In fact, the
effect size was pretty large, about a 50
point reduction. So, a solid, even if
not life-changing effect. Finally, the
holy basil. Well, it turns out that it's
not too holy when it comes to gut
function. There's no evidence out there,
pro or against. However, I'd be doing a
disservice to leave it there because
there are many studies to my surprise on
holy basil, also known as Tulsi. In a
systematic review of 24 clinical trials,
holy basil was identified as having
benefits on blood sugar, blood pressure,
lipids, and more. So out of many of
these ingredients, while it is true that
there's no gut related science, there's
plenty of other reasons to use it. So on
these last three before we move on, for
gut, chia seeds seem decent, though not
much on the microbiome, sauerkraut seems
solid and no evidence for holy basil,
though the wider effects of holy basil
seem to be pretty robust on initial
investigation. Okay, next. Miss Goodman
discusses the optimal pooping frequency
for good health. Now, I honestly never
expected to get myself into so much
crap.
Get it? Do you get the joke I just made?
Brilliant.
Before that, I've made some cursory
mentions to some of these studies like
sauerkraut, activated charcoal, and
antibiotics, lemon juice and extracts,
chlorophyll, and detoxing. And I have a
deeper dive on all these studies in the
extended version of this video that
you're currently watching. It's included
with the Physionic Insiders membership,
including more on applying all these
ingredients if you so choose, plus all
these perks right over here if you have
aren't sold yet. In fact, I'm doing one
of my live sessions this month. So, be
sure to join the community event for
that. Anyway, all my work in video,
audio, and written format, plus
summaries, is supplied to you as a
physionic insider. Link to join is in
the description box. Now, let's discuss
some crap.
>> Wow.
>> Like it. That's another crazy thing cuz
people go Yeah. Once a day. They
>> That's considered constipated these
days.
>> It's crazy. So,
>> walk us through that because that's
always like an uncomfortable topic for
people. It's something that people don't
talk about, but I mean I don't think
we've even we're getting to the point of
understanding how important that the
digestive system is.
>> Yeah.
>> And how often should be people going to
the restroom? What what what should be
the healthy way of um going about that
area of their life?
>> Well, you know, once a day is good,
twice is great, three is perfect. So, we
really because we don't get enough
fiber, because we don't get enough
hydration, because we're stressed
because when we're stressed, our
digestive system completely shuts down.
Um, we are not being able to digest our
food. So, al and also we're eating a lot
of animal protein. So, it takes, you
know, 14 hours to get through the small
intestine, cow and and animal protein,
and 90 minutes for plant-based food,
which is crazy. So, we're
>> Say that difference again. So for
plant-based food, it takes 90 minutes to
get through the small intestine. For cow
and animal protein, it takes 14 hours.
So we're, you know, we're eating eggs
for breakfast and chicken for lunch and
salmon for dinner. Like, so we're just
like, not that it's bad for you, but
we're just we're not getting hydration,
we're not getting fiber, you know, we're
stressed, you're not doing all the
other,
>> we're not doing the other things. We're
not sleeping. Sleeping is very
detoxifying and helping us with our
digestive system. So um, yeah. So, we're
we're supposed to be kind of like an
animal and going after every meal.
>> And people are a little bit like, "Oh,
please don't tell me that."
>> Yeah. Wow. Wow.
>> I know.
>> I just want you to know that if you only
poop once a day, everyone is judging
you. The poop elite, those at two and
three times per day, are infinitely
superior to the mono poopers. Sad to
say, but that's the reality. you need to
step up your in seriousness. Is there
any truth to that claim? So, I'm going
to go a little extreme and then rein it
in because we don't actually know what
perfect means because we don't have an
outcome. So, let's start with your risk
of death relative to the number of times
that you poop. Again, a lot of new
sentences for me today. in long-term
studies quantifying pooping frequency of
people per week and looked at the
association to all-c cause mortality.
Here the 1.0 there indicates a risk if
you poop seven times per week, otherwise
known as once per day on average. If the
blue line goes up, that means there is a
relationship with increased risk of
death. Clearly, pooping less than seven
times per week, more like four times per
week, is linked to risk. However,
pooping two or three times per day does
not seem to offer an improved
relationship over once per day, as
indicated by the lack of movement when
looking at 14 or 21 poops per week. You
know what's interesting? There's even
studies where more than once a day bowel
frequency, that's pooping, is related to
increased risk of death, which would
certainly go against Miss Goodman's
point. Now, the reason for that isn't
quite known. This particular study was
only in women and nurses at that. So
could there be something unique about
that population? Possibly. Is it due to
some other factor not accounted for? For
example, when weight and severe insulin
resistance were accounted for, the
relationship weakened. So clearly some
of it is explained by other factors. The
point here is that there's a good amount
of data that indicates that there's some
uncertainty on the specifics of the
topic, but medical organizations like
the Cleveland Clinic offer a broad range
that of what's considered normal and
healthy with the current data
considered. So they say a broad range of
three times per day all the way up to
three times per week can be perfectly
normal. In fact, they stress that the
bigger tell of poor health may be the
unexpected change in the number of times
that you go, although there are no
drastic dietary or lifestyle changes
that have occurred or blood in your
stool or excess fat in your stool or any
number of very abrupt changes without
reasonable explanation. So, in general,
no. three times per day is a madeup
number and has no strong scientific
evidence yet for it being superior to
two or once per week. So, we can accept
the mono poopers back into our fold. I
sincerely apologize for my elitist
behavior from earlier. Maybe I'm just
full of crap. Now, she mentions a few
other things that I'm going to tackle in
rapid succession. Your digestive system
shuts down from stress. Simon says
there's some truth to that stress can
slow the digestive process though not
entirely shut it down though it depends
on the section of the gastrointestinal
system as the stomach slows emptying and
the colon may actually speed up. Number
two, does animal protein take longer to
go through your intestine than plant
protein? Simon says not so fast. The
reality is there's a lot more to this
statement. For example, if you're
comparing whey protein to casein
protein, they're both animal proteins,
but they're exceptionally different in
how they move through your intestines.
Many hours difference. I do like Miss
Goodman's input on hydration and fiber.
Those also change transit time. So, it's
much more complex and it depends on too
many variables when you're talking about
two very broad categories, all animal
proteins and all plant proteins. Number
three, sleeping helps with your bowel
movements. Simon says, "Yes, that's
true. In fact, some fascinating research
indicates that sleeping slows your
intestinal function significantly during
sleep, but upon waking, it supercharges
it by tripling the speed of your
intestinal passage. If you're watching
the insider version of this video, I'll
show you some fascinating graphs that
illustrate this, but it's not necessary.
The point is the same. Yes, sleep
changes our bowel movements. All right,
we really went over a ton of information
here. So, how do we apply any of this?
What do we make of all this? Well, I'll
mention from the top that Miss Goodman's
recommendations don't have much solid
science behind them. Most have a little
bit of evidence, but none would really
meet the standard of most scientists.
Does that mean that she's wrong on all
counts? No. Keep in mind, science is
often slower than the claims made in the
health influencer circuit. Uh sometimes
those claims end up being true as more
evidence emerges and sometimes it just
gets crushed under the weight of more
and better scientific scrutiny. So then
how should we apply all this? Well, it
depends on what you want and how you
want to think about it. If you are in
camp one, where hard science needs to
back something before you'll consider
it, then for overall health, magnesium
and even potentially holy basil. For gut
health, sauerkraut and chia seeds, you
might throw in some apple cider vinegar
for both, too, but the effects are
really mild, so it may not be worth it.
If you're in camp two, those that would
like to that would like some scientific
backing but are willing to experiment,
then the same options are mentioned, but
maybe consider chlorophyll and kefir
kafir, which are weak or niche in
evidence but also underststudied. As for
the claims surrounding activated
charcoal, there may be some benefit and
it is used in medicine for some
purposes, just nothing really related to
what we've been discussing. The gut
health benefits are mixed and unclear
and the improvement in insulin
resistance is completely
unsubstantiated.
As for how often you should say hello to
the bathroom for bowel appointments,
three times per day has no strong
scientific backing. There's more data
that's needed on the topic, but
generally the greater concern is the
consistency of your poop. Any sudden
changes in frequency, blood in your
poop, and other such abrupt factors. If
you're only pooping once per day or even
slightly less, don't worry about it. It
may be normal for you. And speaking of
crap, there's plenty more science
checking and context to be applied to
health podcasts. And this series on J
Shhatty podcast guest continues right
here if you're so inclined. Thanks for
tuning in. I hope you had a crapload of
fun. Okay, I'll stop. I'll smell you
later. Nicholas, stop it.